<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Vienna the 5. day of August. 1566. of the strong towne and castell of Tula in Hungary xi. myles beyond the riuer Danubius, which was cruelly assaulted by the great Turke, but nowe by Gods mighty working relieued, the sayd Turks marueilouslye discomfited and ouerthrowen. Translated out of hye Almaine into English, and printed in Augspurge by Hans Zimmerman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837892</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1042:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Vienna the 5. day of August. 1566. of the strong towne and castell of Tula in Hungary xi. myles beyond the riuer Danubius, which was cruelly assaulted by the great Turke, but nowe by Gods mighty working relieued, the sayd Turks marueilouslye discomfited and ouerthrowen. Translated out of hye Almaine into English, and printed in Augspurge by Hans Zimmerman.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Awdeley, dwelling in litle Britaine streete without Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The 21. of Septmember. 1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "A prayer of thankesgeuyng, for the defence of the Christians agaynst the cruel Turke".</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration on title page.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vienna (Austria) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2239:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Newes from Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna the .5. day of Auguſt .1566. of the ſtrong Towne and Caſtell of Iula in Hungary, xl. myles beyond the riuer Danubius, which was cruelly aſſaulted by the great Turke, but nowe by Gods mighty working relieued, &amp; the ſayd Turke marueylouſlye diſcomfited and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. Tranſlated out of hye Almaine into Engliſh, and printed in Augſpurge by Hans Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merman.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of a battle</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Iohn Awdeley, dwelling in litle Britaine ſtreete without Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. The .21. of September. 1566.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2239:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2239:2"/>
            <head>¶ Newes from Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna the .5. day of Auguſt .1566. of the Turkes ouerthrow:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the Emperour of Turkie had beſieged with an army of thirty thouſand horſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and footemen, the famous town and ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Caſtel of Iula in Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gary, lying .xl. dutch myles beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ryuer Danubius, which City had by the ſpace of .vj. weekes ſuſtayned many greuous aſſaultes: God through his great mercy and goodnes ſo com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forted the ſayd towne of Iula and the poore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians therein, at their earneſt praiers, that the Turke with all his hoſt was driuen backe, by the handes of the General called Keretſhim Laſlawe and hys valiant company. Who not onelye defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſayd Towne, but alſo conſtrayned the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Turkes to retyre, to their great ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſlaughter of a great nomber of their Turkiſh rable. For the which the euerliuyng God be prayſed for euer. The manner of their ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw was thys.</p>
            <p>As the foreſayd Generall Keretſhim did ſe his aduauntage, wyth Captayne George and other horſmen of Scheſians and Hungary, he ſet vpon the arereward of the Turkes, and kylled about .8. thouſand of them, and tooke alſo ſome of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery,
<pb facs="tcp:2239:3"/> and followed them ſo faſt, that the Turkes were conſtrayned to flee into a marriſh grounde, and to breake the wheeles of the reſt of their artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, to ſaue them ſelues: which the Chriſtians al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo tooke, and haue reſcued and taken beſydes from the Turkes a great nomber of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſoners, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rewyth a very rych bootye.</p>
            <p>The like alſo hath done that valiant man Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gotſrhie the Captayne of Erla, the which making toward the Turkes, did encounter with the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, ſetting moſt valiantly vpon them, and kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led about eyght hundred of them.</p>
            <p>A few dayes paſt the Earle of Serin did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with a Turkiſh Capitayne called Begen, the which Capitaine then had with him a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d freſh horſmen then comming out of Turkye, to go to a towne called Fynffekyrchen. Which Earle did ſet vpon them in the night, and killed the Captain, and tooke .vjij. Camels, and .viii. Moyles laden wyth treaſure, and got alſo twoo read Gwydons, wyth a whole great peece of rych cloth of gold, and alſo a very fayre and ſtraunge Iewel or token of the field. This foreſayd Earle dyd ſende vnto the Emperours Maieſty to Vienna for a preſent, the foreſayd Captaynes horſe, the which was not one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry fayre one and good, but alſo betrapped &amp; decked moſte rychly. For fyrſt the poniel &amp; the back part of the ſaddel was couered ouer with plate of fine Arabick gold, and the reſt of the ſaddel beſyde the ſytting place, was dreſt wyth ſyluer plate very
<pb facs="tcp:2239:3"/> fyre gilded, which ſitting place was couered with a fine purple veluet, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trappers &amp; bridle beſet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> litle Turkies and Rubies. The Earle would very fayne haue ſaued the ſayd Capitayne, but the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Ianyſſery defended them ſelues ſo manfully, thinking to haue caryed away ſafelye their Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid Earle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys company was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to kyll both them and their Captayne.</p>
            <p>Alſo this valiant Earle of Serin hath got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other great prices from the Turkes .xv. thouſand Turkiſh and Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gariſh Ducates, which money was brought for the payment of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſhe men of warre, which are in the towne called Fynffkyrchen. Thus not onely this ſaid Earle had got to himſelfe rich and great prices, but alſo hys Souldiours haue met with very rich prayes and ſpoyles.</p>
            <p>And now to declare the Mahometical and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh cruelty of theſe helliſh Turks, which they vſe agaynſt the Chriſtians (which cannot be declared without weeping and ſorowfulnes of mynde) is this in effect. Where euer they ouercome the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and take them captiues, they take the yong and luſty men tying them to their horſes &amp; famiſhe them to death. The old men and women they cut in peeces, deflouring the maydens and young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men very villanouſly. The ſely Infants and yong Babes lying in their cradels ſmyling vpon them, they take out very cruelly and ſticke them on long poles and ſo gore them to death without pitye or
<pb facs="tcp:2239:4"/> mercy, and this very ſpitefully they do in the ſight of the Infantes Parentes. The reſidue of them which they keepe alyue being men, they vſe as be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ites for all kynde of drudgery and toyle, more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly entreating them then their brute beaſtes. To the women and children whych they keepe alyue, they vſe ſuch Sodomiſh abhomination and tyran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny as may not for ſhame be knowen, nor wythout harty ſorow be declared. Wherefore it behoueth al Chriſtian Princes and good Chriſtians to wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thys cruel Turckiſh enemy, &amp; to ſet to theyr helpyng handes, ſuch as can to helpe to reſiſt hym with ſome power of warre: and ſuche other good Chriſtians as cannot helpe theſe our Chriſtian bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſo cruelly aſſaulted) by this kinde of meanes: yet at leaſt to helpe them with their godly praiers. For if thus he proceede forwarde to take the vpper land, it wyl redound to the great plague and ruine of whole Chriſtendome. Wherefore that thus it may not come to pas, let vs not ceaſe to cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our heauenly father for his mightye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, who ſo mercifully hath heard the praiers of his poore afflicted children. And alſo geue him hartye thankes for this great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of thys his Chriſtes and our cruell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:2239:4"/>
            <head>A Prayer &amp; thankes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geuyng, for the defence of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians agaynſt the cruel Turke.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternal God and moſt mercyfull father we geue thee harty thanks for this thy mightye woorking in ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing that curſed and cruell Turke, the enemy of thy deare ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and hys deare Chriſtians, and for re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieuing his poore afflicted members, in deliuering them from his and their bloo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy handes: Wherefore (deare father) we beſeche thee to continue in this thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful defending them, and in ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his tirannical power, that they here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may wel feele and know, that ther is none other God beſides thee &amp; thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. Preſerue (O Lord) thoſe godlye &amp; Chriſtian Princes which venter their liues againſt this thi enemy, as namely the Emperours Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty with his two brethren, and all hys whole nobility, geuing them proſperous ſucces &amp; victorious conqueſt. Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this O Father for thy deare ſonnes ſake Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Sauiour. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
